PRESENTER: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content
video for AWS, VSCode,
and GitHub setup.
All right.
So we're going to
cover in this video
how to create an EC2 instance,
download the VSCode setup
script, login to VSCode web
client and run Python files,
and how to stop and start
the EC2 instance so you
can shut it down when you
want and then start it up
when you want.
All right, let's get into it.
So this video assumes that you
already have an AWS account.
They're easy to set up.
There's no cost to set them up.
And if you just
watch your spending,
there's a lot of ways to keep it
really, really cheap or no cost.
So it's a good
production-level tool
that you can do on the cheap.
OK, so here's what
we're going to do.
We're going to create
a EC2 instance.
So EC2 stands for
Elastic Computing 2.
Click on EC2 or search it
in the Search Bar above.
And then you want to get to
the page, that's Instances.
So on the left here
click on Instances.
And then I'm going to
create a new instance here.
And the way to do that is launch
an instance at the top right.
So the top right,
Launch Instance.
And name it to the
name of the class.
There we go.
So I'm going to name mine
5500 for this video here.
Then make sure to select Ubuntu
right here, Ubuntu as the image.
Ubuntu is the operating
system you're going to use.
There it is right there.
The instance type, you
can leave it as a t2 micro
because later on if you find
that you need more memory,
you can upgrade it later.
But t2 micros are free and it'll
let you get everything working
and set up and use it
for a while for free.
And then one more thing you
need to do on this screen
is allow for HTTPS
traffic from the internet.
The VSCode web client
that you're going
to be coding on uses HTTPS.
So you need to set up
HTTPS on the correct port
and establish your certificate.
So that needs to be checked.
And then do launch
instance and it'll say,
do you want to
create a key pair.
I'm going to proceed without
a key pair, and you can, too.
What that means is if you
wanted to log into that server
with using an SSH tool,
you could do that.
We're not going to do that.
The main way we log into the
server is going to be VSCode.
So there's no need to
do a key pair right now.
So there we go.
Proceed without key pair,
and then hit Launch instance.
And then I'm going to pull
up two screens at once here.
So I've got my instances screen.
And you can see my
data 5500 server
that I just created is in
running state right now.
And then I'm going to go
over here and connect to it.
So then in this screen, this was
the screen after you hit Launch.
Hit Connect to instance.
It'll take me to the
Connect Instance screen,
and then I hit Connect.
All right, then
we are connected.
So now that our server
is created for us,
we're going to
download everything
we need to create a VSCode
web client on this server
that we can use to
write and run code.
So I created a GitHub
repo for everybody to use.
So all of the scripts
setup is done for you.
You can just download
it and run them.
So the GitHub repo is
github.com/andrewbrimusu/EC2
scripts.
And if you go there, and then
there's a little setup page
and explains what's going on.
And if you scroll down,
there's a setup instructions
for clone this repo and
run the setup files.
And you can just do
it just like that.
So you can copy
that right there.
Go back to your server
here, your server terminal.
And then literally just paste
it right in there and hit Enter.
And that'll do everything
you need for you.
It's going to download
your VSCode client.
It's going to get all
the libraries you need
and it's going to set
up a HTTPS certificate
so that you can connect to your
VSCode securely over HTTPS.
And that is going to take
about five minutes to run.
So I'm going to go ahead
and pause this video
while all of those
files download.
See you in a second.
So all of the files
were downloaded
and the server has
been set up now.
I just want to
point out one thing
before I log into the server.
If you look at the very
bottom of the output,
the default password is
changeme exclamation point.
So the first time
you log into VSCode,
it'll ask for a password,
that's what it'll be.
And then I'll show you in just
a minute how you can change that
to something else.
All right.
So now that that's set up, the
way to connect to your VSCode
web client, it uses the same
IP address as the EC2 instance.
So the easiest way
I found to find it
is just go to the Instances page
and then click on the instance
ID of your server.
In my case, it's data.
The name of the
server is data 5500.
I'm going to click
on the instance ID.
And then you can see
in the top right here,
this public IP 4v DNS.
Click just the open
address right there.
And then notice for
a second it says
your connection is not private.
It is a secure
certificate of downloads
over a secure connection.
The reason you're
getting this warning,
though, is the
certificate has not
been authenticated by a
third-party service which
performs authentication.
That's because you're going to
be the only person connecting
to this website, but
it is over HTTPS.
It does use a
secure certificate.
And it's password-protected.
So you can proceed, or
click advance proceed.
And then here is
where you're going
to enter that default password,
changeme exclamation point.
And voila.
So here is your
VSCode web client
running on an EC2 instance.
I'm going to click Yes,
I trust the authors.
And then let me show
you one more thing
here or a couple things.
So if you look under your files
and folders in the top left
here, you can see this .config.
If you expand that guy and
then open up the config.yaml,
I'm going to change it here to
changeme, again, exclamation.
You can change yours to
something more secure
and then your password
will be good to go.
OK, the last thing I'm going
to show you in this video
is how to create Python
files and run them,
and then how to shut it
down so you can save money
so it's not running
all the time,
and then how to start
it back up again.
All right.
So now that we've got
our environment here,
I'm going to make a new
folder for all of my code.
I don't want it in that folder.
One second.
No, I don't want there.
Let me see if I
can move it there.
So I'm going to make
just a folder, a test
folder for some Python files.
Hello, and then
drag it up there.
No, drag it up there.
Go up there.
There we go.
Wow, that's new file, hello.py.
I want this whole thing
to go in my Ubuntu folder.
There we go.
Come on back there.
All right, we'll do
this another way here.
I'm going to do it like this.
Let me go to View, Terminal.
And then in my
terminal, I'm going
to do Panel Position, Right.
And then do make dir.hello.
There we go.
So now I've got my folder.
Check it over on the left here.
Hello, and I'm going to
right click New File in there
and do a hello.py.
Here we go.
And then just print hello world.
Looks good.
Now, when you click on
that file on the left
and then click this little
run-in debug, it'll say,
hey, I don't have
a Python extension
and then you'll download one.
You only need to do this once.
So on the Python,
click Install Python
and then click Install
Python debugger.
And let those two
run for a second.
There we go.
And now you'll see
when it's done,
there will be a little run
button on the top right now.
And I can run, and there it is.
So now I can run my Python.
So this is where you'll run
your code and your homework
and your final project,
and in-class exercises
and things like that.
The last thing I'm going
to show you in this video
is how to shut it down so you're
not charged when you're not
using your server.
So simply go back to
your EC2 Instances page
and then click on
the-- hang on a second.
Let me refresh.
There we go.
So I got my data 5500
server Instance state.
Stop.
Do not terminate.
Terminate will delete it and
it will be gone for good.
So just stop it.
I'm going to stop
it right there.
And then you will not
get charged for it.
And it's actually, if you're
vigilant about stopping
or starting your server,
then working on it,
then stopping it when you're
done, AWS is very inexpensive.
And if you aren't
a t2 micro, like I
am, if you can see where my
mouse is hovering right there,
t2 micro, those are
free-tier eligible.
So I think you get--
how many hours?
I forget how many hours--
you get a free usage.
So it's actually very
inexpensive to run a t2 micro,
if you remember to stop it.
Even if you don't.
If you leave it on
all the time, 24/7,
it'll be about $15
to $20 a month.
But if you're vigilant
about stopping it,
it'll be free or near free.
OK, it's still stopping,
but let me refresh.
I think it stopped.
OK, so it stopped now.
Now, let's say you want to
log in or class is starting,
you're going to log in and
start coding or working
on your homework.
From here, you just
click on your server
and then do Instance
state, start this time.
You can see it went into
pending state right there.
Now, it's in running.
So I'm going to click
on the instance ID here.
And again-- oh, one
more thing here.
Before you can open up
the VSCode web client,
you actually need to connect to
the server as the user Ubuntu.
So the default user on the
server is the name Ubuntu.
That's the username.
And it needs to log in
to the server as Ubuntu.
So rather than just
clicking and going straight
to your VSCode web
client, you do actually
need to connect
to the server once
and you can see what
happened as I connected.
It said starting Code
server on port 443.
So once you log in as
that user, then it'll
fire up automatically
the VSCode web client.
Then you're good to go.
So then come back here.
Click on the link to the
server via the web client.
Let me close that.
That's the old one.
That's the old one, too.
Close that.
Oh, hang on.
Let me double
check that it's up.
If you want to, what I do
to double check that it's up
is you can hit bash.
That'll recreate an environment
for the Ubuntu user.
Maybe the IP is different.
Let me double check
that real quick.
All right.
So it's definitely running.
Let me go back here.
Make sure I'm on the
right instance one second.
Yeah, that looks
good, data 5500.
And open address.
There we go.
So click Advanced.
You only have to
cast a certificate
once every time
the server is up.
So there we go.
And then I think I changed
it to changeme again.
Bang.
And yours obviously
will be something else.
And then voila,
we are connected.
So that concludes this video
on creating a EC2 instance,
loading the VSCode web client,
and creating and running
Python files.
Thanks for watching.